(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-07T02:04:10.804337",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
グッドモーニングのじゃあ～
Good morning, noja~
のじゃあ～
Noja~
よいしょ
Yoisho
あーー
Ahhh...
あいさつするのじゃあ？
Greeting us, noja?
あらあら、めらめら、あちちめら！
Oh my, Mela Mela, Achichi Mela!
ホロライブ遊びまわりたい、ゴリヤクダン等のひけしやさらまんダー、あちち、めらなのじゃあ！
Want to play around in Hololive! Goriyakudan and other firefighters and salamanders... Achichi, Mela noja!
のじゃ、BGMふたつになった
Noja. BGM became two.
のじゃ、のじゃ、おはようのじゃあ！
Noja, noja. Good morning, noja!
グッドモーニング or グッドイブニング or ハローなのじゃ
Good morning, or good evening, or hello, noja!
のじゃ、落ちちゃった？ のじゃ
Noja. Did it drop? Noja.
のじゃあ～、のじゃあ～、大丈夫
Noja~ Noja~ It's okay.
聞こえる？ 聞こえるのじゃあ？ のじゃあ
Can you hear? Can you hear, noja? Noja~
You guys ok? オッケーのじゃ、オンライン
You guys ok? Okay, noja. Online.
I'm back. あ、Thank youのじゃあ！
I'm back. Ah, thank you, noja!
よかった… Thank youのじゃあ、のじゃあ
Good... Thank you, noja. Noja.
切れちゃったっぽい。ええっと、ちょっと待ってほしいのじゃ
Looks like it disconnected. Um... Please wait a moment, noja.
ちょっと待ってほしいのじゃ。なんか設定が難しくって…
Please wait a moment, noja. Somehow the settings are difficult...
あんまりまだわかってない
And I don't really understand them yet.
よいしょ。え、また切れた？ わとわと、のじゃ、何じゃ
Yoisho. Eh, it disconnected again? What what, noja. What is it.
今、オッケ？今オッケ？ラグい、BGMふたびのじゃあ
Now ok? Now ok? Laggy. BGM again, noja!
トラブル、めにめにとらぶる！ソーリー？ソーリーなのじゃ
Trouble, many, many troubles! Sorry? Sorry, noja!
どうしよう、ソーリーのじゃ
What should I do, sorry, noja!
のじゃあ、オッケ、オッケ、オッケ、のじゃあ、さらごめんのじゃあ
Noja~ Ok, ok, ok, noja! Sorry, Mela, noja!
よいしょ、よいしょ。もう朝なのに、モーニングなのにいっぱいトラブル
Yoisho, yoisho. Even though it's morning, even though it's morning, so many troubles!
いっぱいトラブルって…あの起きた、I wake up. 逆にね
So many troubles... I woke up, I wake up. Actually, no...
逆に起きたのじゃ。おはようなのじゃあ…
I actually woke up, noja. Good morning, noja~
あのね、あのね、あのね、今日は…
You know, you know, you know, today is...
のじゃイングリッシュだからいっぱい寝た。あの…
Noja English so I slept a lot! Um...
8時間寝た、I sleep.
I slept 8 hours. I sleep.
えいとはわー、あってる？
Eight hours, is that right?
うん、早く寝たよ。昨日十時、二十二時に寝た。
Yeah, I went to sleep early. Yesterday at 10, 10 PM.
二十二時に寝ましたのじゃ。今日の朝のためにそれであね、六時、シックスに起きた。
I went to sleep at 10 PM, you see. So that I'd be ready for this morning, I woke up at 6, at 6.
いっぱい寝ましたのじゃ。
Full of sleep, you see.
いっぱい寝たのじゃ！
That's a good amount of sleep!
いっぱい寝ましたのじゃ。
I got plenty of sleep, you see.
そっちはまだ夜？
The other side is still night?
ユーガイズ、ナイト、ナイト。
You guys, night, night.
ジャパン　イズ　モーニング。
Japan is morning.
午後6時、シックスPM。
6 PM... 6 PM.
ミッドナイト、6PM here.
Midnight, 6 PM here.
あるいはイブニング？そうか、イブニングだ。
Or evening? Evening, right?
イレブンPM、いっぱいの時間、メニータイム、メニータイム、メッツナイト、深夜。
11 PM, so many times, midnight, yeah, midnight.
ライジングサン。
Rising sun.
そうそう、つづり、つづりと言っても、あの、遊びに行きたいメンバーの
Let's see, Tsuzuri and Kyoko...
つづり＆きょこは、あの、ストリー、ストリーミングなの。ずっとね、あの、配信、
Tsuzuri and Kyoko are streaming, you know?
バロラント？バロラント？オーバーウォッチ？
Valorant? Valorant? Overwatch?
ごめん、げ、ゲームがちゃんと理解できてない。
Wait, I don't really understand games.
あの、FPS、FPSのなんか耐久配信をしてた。
FPS... FPS's endurance stream, they were doing.
そう、ロング、ロングストリームをね、してた。
So, long, long stream, they were doing.
オーバーウォッチ、オーバーウォッチをね、してた。
Overwatch, Overwatch, they were doing.
Yes long long stream, Overwatch maybe.
今から2人、めっちゃ頑張ってるのじゃ、すごいのだ。
They're working so hard, that's amazing, right?
Crazy!
確かに、確かにめっちゃ長い。うん、体力、体力すごいのだ。
Yeah, it's really long. Their stamina is amazing!
なんか気合入れてたよ。うん。
They're putting in so much effort.
で、メーラはイングリッシュスタディストリームを...
And Mela's English study stream...
するんじゃが、あのね、あの、前回のデュオリンゴの配信で
Well, you know, in the last Duolingo stream...
あの、お主らめっちゃ簡単って思わなかった？
Didn't you think Mela was super smart?
あの、Duolingo was too easy、あの、前のストリーム、そう、でと思って、そう、I tried、あの、テスト、スキッピング、そう、飛び級？飛び級しようと思って、I tried skipping head to section 3, so section 2 was too easy, so, uh, I tried skipping it.
Because the Duolingo was too easy, I thought, in the last stream, so I tried skipping...
そう、バット、しかし、あの、I failed!
So, but, however, I failed!
そう、難しくて、It's hard for me. そう、難しかった。難しくて、あの、セクション3が、あの、ダメ、ダメだった！
So, it was difficult, and it was hard for me.
I can't skip! そう、Too difficult for me.
I can't skip! So, it's too difficult for me.
そう、ダメじゃった！から、あの、
So, it was no good, and from now on...
またいつか挑戦する。うん、またいつか挑戦するから、ベーシックからやろうと思うのじゃ。
I'm going to try again sometime, start from the basics.
え、もう一回お主らと一緒にやってみる？
Shall we try doing it with Mela again?
今日の朝やってダメだったやつ、もう一回お主らとやってみる？
The one we tried this morning and failed, let's try it again with Mela.
ちょっとどんなのか見てみる？いったん。いったん見てみろ、お主ら。
Let's check what it's like first, shall we?
You, you guys want to see test?
You guys want to see the test?
じゃ、一回見せてあげる。一回見せてあげるのじゃ。うん。
I'll show you once.
えっと、じゃあお勉強のお部屋に行こうと思うから、あ、
Well, then, let's go to the study room. Oh...
You guys, already push like?
You guys already pushed like?
Already like my video? グッドボタンを押してくれましたかのじゃ？
Did you press the like button, you see?
Please subscribe to my channel, and push like, good button to take off my mask, no ja!
Please subscribe to my channel, and push like and the good button...
take off my mask, no ja!
To take off my mask, you see!
あー
Ah...
ありがと、のじゃのじゃ。じゃあ行くのじゃ、よいしょ！
Thank you, noja noja! Now let's go, heave-ho!
おはようのじゃ～
Good morning, noja~
で、えーと、アイ、でどれだっけ？
And, um, I... which one was it?
そう、This is Section 2.
That's right, This is Section 2.
前回やったのがこれね。これがセクション2で
What I did last time is this. This is Section 2 and
で、Section 2んで、I tried this. Section 3
And, Section 2... and, I tried this. Section 3...
I know some words in English.
そう。ちょっとは単語知ってますよ、英語の。
Right. I know a few words, you know, in English.
そう。ちょっとは英単語知ってますの特に、あの、飛び級しようと思って。
Right. Especially since I know a few English words, I thought I'd skip ahead.
I tried this.
そう、Actually I think I know some word in English, 知ってると思う。
Right. Actually, I think I know some words in English, I think I know them.
そう。ジニンネ？ワシは、知ってるつもりジャンプだからこれをやったんじゃけど
Right. Honestly? Since I thought I knew it, I jumped ahead and did this, but
オッケー、アイ、見せてあげる。
Okay, I... I'll show you.
このテストをクリアして「セクション3」まで飛び級しよう！
Pass this test to skip ahead to Section 3!
で、やろうとしたの、充電する、チャージ。
And what I tried to do, recharging, charge.
あ、音聞こえるお主ら。チャージ。でかいかな？
Ah, can you hear the sound, guys? Charge. Is it loud?
Is to big? Charge. どう？じゃあ、sounds good?
Is it too big? Charge. How is it? Then, sounds good?
うるさい？いい感じかな？大きい？オッケーオッケー、too big, オッケー？
Is it noisy? Is it good? Is it loud? Okay okay, too big, okay?
チャージ。オッケー？It's ok? いい感じか、オッケーグッド、オッケーオッケーオッケー。
Charge. Okay? It's ok? Is it good, okay good, okay okay okay.
じゃあ、これで。チャージ、充電する。待って、前回と問題違う！問題が違うのじゃ！
Then, with this. Charge, recharge. Wait, the questions are different from last time! The questions are different, noja!
オッケー。次へ、えっと
Okay. Next, um...
Is this place safe?
ここは、ここは安全ですか？
Here is... Is this place safe?
え、今回簡単かも！前回よりも、あの、イージー、イージーかも。
Eh, this time might be easy! Compared to last time, um, it might be easy, easy.
前もっと簡単、難しかった。
Before, it was much easier... harder.
忘れる、フォーゲット、フォーゲット。
To forget, forget, forget.
え、なんか前回より簡単かも！え、運ゲーなのじゃ？これ。
Eh, somehow it might be easier than last time! Eh, is it luck-based, noja? This.
Don't wear shoes inside.
ええと、室内で、えー、靴を履かないでください。
Um, indoors, um... please do not wear shoes.
え、運ゲー、ご利益担当なのじゃ？これもしもし、もしかしてこれ、あの、配信、配信で運がいい、わしのやつ？のじゃ？
Eh, is this luck-based, blessing duty, noja? Could this possibly be, um, stream luck, is this my stream? Noja?
普段よりも実力が、あれか？そう、question changed.
Is my skill better than usual? That's right, question changed.
変えちゃったの、バフが、バフが乗ってるのじゃ。
It changed, a buff, a buff is active, noja.
橋、ブリッジ、ブリッジ。
Bridge, bridge, bridge.
え、配信バフ可能性ありのじゃ。ブリッジ。
Eh, stream buff is a possibility, noja. Bridge.
Don't drive on that road.
えーっと、その道で、運転しないで。
Um, on that road, do not drive.
え、イージー！
Eh, easy!
待て、楽しむ、ハヴファン、ハヴファン。
Wait, to enjoy, have fun, have fun.
デュオリンゴイズウォッチングマイストリーム？
Duolingo is watching my stream?
デュオリンゴを見てる？ハリー、ユー、アー、レイト！遅いから早よせい！
Duolingo is watching? Hurry, you are late! You're slow, hurry up!
え、待って、まだライフが3ある。ライフ0になったのに。マジのじゃ？
Eh, wait, I still have 3 lives. Even though my lives went to 0. Seriously, noja?
のじゃあ、え、イージーイージー。ビー、なんちゃら、This area is dangerous at night. Be careful, noja. Carefull.
Noja, eh, easy easy. Be, whatever, This area is dangerous at night. Be careful, noja. Careful.
え、イージーのじゃ、イージーのじゃ。
Eh, easy noja, easy noja.
いくら使っていますか？ How much are you...
How much are you spending? How much are you...
How much are you spending？じゃない？のじゃ？え、イージーイージー、ツーイージーのじゃ、ホワイ、なんで？なんでのじゃ？
How much are you spending? Right? Noja? Eh, easy easy, too easy noja, why, why? Why noja?
もっと難しかったのじゃ。
It was much harder.
忘れちゃったじゃん。どんな問題じゃったかも忘れてないけど、なんかむず、むずって思ったじゃん。
I forgot... what problem was that?
マニーのじゃ。え?簡単すぎないのじゃ?ホワイ?なんで?
Money! Too easy, isn't it? Why?
のじゃあああ！
Nojaaa!
トゥーイージーですのじゃ。なんで?
Too easy, isn't it, Noja? Why?
こんなのある？こんなのある！？
Is that even a thing? Is that even a thing?!
そのことは心配しないで。Don't worry about that.
Don't worry about that.
えっ？待って、イージーイージー！ホワイ？
Huh? Wait, easy, easy! Why?
え、もしかしてわし、あのセクション4、4、4チャレンジしてた？のじゃ？
Wait, was I challenging section 4? Noja?
Please...
Come...
...inside.
トゥーイージーのじゃ！トゥーイージーのじゃ！
Too easy, Noja! Too easy, Noja!
一緒に橋を渡ろう。えー、あ、これわかんない。えー、レッツ、レッツ
Let's cross...
レッツ、なんちゃらブリッジ、ブリッジ、togetherだと思うんだよ、together。レッツ
Let's bridge together.
渡るってなんだろう？レッツ、パス、パスとか。ちょ一旦これで、のじゃ！
Let's pass bridge together.
クロスザストリート。ブリッジじゃないのじゃ？クロス、クロス
Cross the street.
あ、道！橋だと思った。橋じゃない！道なのじゃ！
Not a bridge, it's a road!
アベニューとブリッジ、日本語、ジャパニーズ間違えたのじゃ。
Avenue and bridge, I got the Japanese wrong, Noja.
マイ、ジャパニーズイズバッド、のじゃ。クロスザストリートトゥギャザー、のじゃ。
Cross the street together, Noja.
私たちはプールに泳ぎに行きます。We...
We...
わし英語苦手、英訳超苦手、英訳超苦手。We...あー、going...we are going... swimming, swimming
We are going swimming.
のじゃ！
Noja!
プールにがない。We are going, going swimming... at the pool?
There's no "to"! We are going... swimming... at the pool?
なんでトウないの？なんでトウないのじゃ？ワイ？ワイノトウ？ワイノトウ？イングが重複？イング、トウイングはだめ？ワイ？ワイ、ノットバット
Why is there no "to"? Why no "to"? "Swimming" is a gerund?
We are going swimming at the pool... to the pool or going swimming... to the pool... 不定詞？トゥ不定詞？わかんない言葉来た！不定詞来た不定詞！We are going to swim?
We are going to swim?
goingでイングを使うならto swim？toがあるならswim？toのあとにingがつかない？
If you use "going", it's "to swim"? If you have "to", it's "swim"? No "-ing" after "to"?
to swim or swimming？not to swimming. To...toはだめ。be ing toで未来系？ビー、ビーがアーじゃろ。
"Be going to" for future? "Be" is "are"?
イング、ゴイング。あ、toのあと、スウィミングの時点だめなのか？
-ing... going... Oh, "-ing" after "to" isn't allowed?
be going to動詞。be going to動詞なのじゃ。でも、toがもう半会頭にないからだめなのじゃ。
"Be going to" + verb... But "to" isn't in the options, so it's no good?
to swim what you will do. Swimming what you are doing. ああ、じゃあ、to swimでもいいな。Swimming what you are doing. でも、およ、泳
"To swim what you will do"? "Swimming what you are doing"?
行い で いる 状態 に なる ?
Becoming a state of doing it?
Go to swim なら オーケー 。
If it's 'go to swim', it's okay.
To swim なら 大丈夫 。
If it's 'to swim', it's fine.
We are going to swim...
@ ザ プール でも オーケー 。
or 'at the pool' is also okay.
Go swimming が 泳ぎ に 行く 。
'Go swimming' means going to swim.
Go to swim が 泳ぐ ため に 行く 。
'Go to swim' means going in order to swim.
あ 、 意味 が 変わっ ちゃう の じゃん 。
Ah, the meaning changes.
細かい ニュアンス が 変わっ ちゃ うっぽい 。
The subtle nuances seem to change.
どっち も オーケー だ けど なん か より 良い ニュアンス に する に は
Both are okay, but if you want a better nuance,
Goen... ん ? Going swimming ?
Goen... Hm? Going swimming?
に なる っぽい 。
seems to be it.
Going swimming が 自然 な 表現 。 オーケー 。
'Going swimming' is the natural expression. Okay.
じゃあ これ は 不 自然 な 表現 な の じゃ ? Going swimming ?
Then is this an unnatural expression? Going swimming?
Go shopping ...
Go shopping...
オーケー 、 じゃあ なん か なん とか し に 行き ます の 場合 は 、
Okay, so if you go to do something,
でも 正解 で は Going swimming だ から な 。
but the correct answer is 'going swimming'.
え ? ing が 2 回 来る の 不思議 な 感じ する の じゃ 。
Eh? Having 'ing' twice feels weird.
不思議 な 感じ する 。
It feels weird.
ちょっと これ は あの 経験 で なん とか する しか ない の じゃ 。 オーケー 。
Well, you just have to get used to it through experience. Okay.
驚異 の 集中 力 ! 次 へ 。
Incredible focus! Next.
え 、 でも パス 、 パス か も パス 。
Wait, but pass, maybe pass? Pass.
パス し た かも 。
Maybe I passed.
オーケー だっ た かも の じゃ 。
It might have been okay.
ロック さ れ た ?
Unlocked?
アンロック の じゃ ?
セクション 3 に チャレンジ 券 が ある !
There's a challenge ticket for Section 3!
見て ユー ガイズ 見て ! ロック の じゃ !
Look, you guys, look! It's unlocked!
セクション 3 いける !
Section 3, here I go!
やった ! やった の じゃ !
Yay! Yay!
なんか 配信 前 の 朝 試し た 時 は 、 あの ライフ ゼロ 、 最後 の 和訳 の ところ で ゼロ じゃっ た ん じゃ が 合格 し た の じゃ !
When I tried it in the morning, my lives were at 0, but I passed!
やった の じゃ !
Yay!
最初 の ing は 未来 を 示し て 、 あと の ing は 動詞 名詞 。 出 た 動詞 名詞 !
The first 'ing' is the future, and the second is a gerund. Gerund!
あの わし が 授業 で 聞い て 全く わかん なかっ た やつ !
The one I heard in class and didn't understand at all!
ジャパニーズ お前 ら は 動詞 名詞 とか 理解 し てる の じゃ ?
Japanese people, do you understand gerunds and things like that?
授業 で 理解 でき た タイプ ? わし は わかん なかっ た 。
Did you understand it in class? I didn't get it.
わし は 動詞 名詞 とか そう いう の わかん なかっ た の じゃ 。
I didn't understand gerunds and things like that.
はい 、 ちゃんと 理解 しろ 、 動詞 名詞 の じゃ 。
Yes, make sure you understand gerunds.
覚える ぞ 。 覚える の じゃ 。
I'm going to memorize it. Memorize it.
これから ね 、 学ぶ の じゃ 。 わし と 一緒 に 覚える の じゃ 。
I will learn from now on. Memorize it with me.
雰囲気 じゃ なく て ね 、 確実 に 覚える の じゃ 。
Not just by vibe, but memorizing it for sure.
オーケー 、 じゃあ セクション 3 ! 運動 について 話す 。
Okay, then Section 3! Talking about exercise.
運動 って なん じゃ ? スポーツ ?
What is exercise? Sports?
Talk about sports な の じゃ 。
It's 'Talk about sports'.
行く の じゃ !
Let's go!
キャッチ ?
Catch?
ボール を キャッチ し て
Catch the ball.
オーケー な の じゃ 。
Okay.
Wow, you read fast !
Wow, you read fast!
わあ 、 ユー レッド ファスト 。
Wow, you read fast.
あなた は 読む の が 早い よ 。
You read quickly.
That player always catches the ball.
ザ プレーヤー オールウェイズ キャッチズ ザ ボール 。
The player always catches the ball.
その プレーヤー は いつも ボール を キャッチ する 。
That player always catches the ball.
空振り し ない ? 空振り し ない の じゃ 。
Doesn't miss? Doesn't miss.
この 辺 は イージー な の じゃ 。 I can understand ディース 。 わかる 。
This part is easy. I can understand this. I get it.
Why do you always walk fast ?
Why do you always walk fast?
えっと 、 Why do you always ... Why do you always walk fast ?
Why do you always... Why do you always walk fast?
なんで いつも 早く 歩く の ?
Why do you always walk fast?
もっと ゆっくり 歩い て ほしい の じゃ 。
I want you to walk more slowly.
Writing sentences is the hardest for yes. そう 。
Writing sentences is the hardest for yes. That's right.
そう 、 I'm not good at あの 和訳
Yeah, I'm not good at translation.
ジャパニーズにイングリッシュトゥジャパニーズ、ん？ノージャパニーズトゥイングリッシュができない。
Japanese to English to Japanese... Wait, I can't do Japanese to English.
そう、それができないのじゃ。
Right, I can't do that, you see.
次。空欄を埋めてください。「I run fast. 早く走れます。」
Next. Please fill in the blank: "I run fast."
「She can run fast. 彼女も早く走れます。」トム
"She can run fast." Tom...
トムきゃんさーふ？ なんかひとりだけ違う。
Tom can surf? Wait, why is just one different?
トムはドリブルがうまい！
Tom is great at dribbling!
いい感じ！のじゃのじゃ。
Looking good! Noja-noja.
なんで走りの話してるのにトムだけ、トムだけ、
Why is everyone talking about running, but Tom...
トムだけサーフの話？わい、わいトム？サーフ？わいサーフ！何なのじゃー？
Tom is the only one talking about surfing? Why surf?!
次。「Yes, I can surf well.」トムきた。
Next. "Yes, I can surf well." Here comes Tom.
「Yes, I can surf well.」私は、あのサーフィンめっちゃ上手できますよ、おー。
"Yes, I can surf well." Oh, I am so good at surfing...
ヒーじゃないよね。「can fast to run fast to」早く走りや、ってこと？
It's not "he", right? "Can fast to run fast to..."
あ、「He can run fast too」早く走りやっってこと？
Ah, "He can run fast too"! Run fast too, is that it?
あ、一個じゃないのか！オンリーワンじゃとトムった。なるほど。
Ah, it's not just one! I thought it was only one option.
サーフィンもできるし、早く走ることもできますよってことか。オーケーオーケー。
He can surf and also run fast, is that it? Oki, oki.
「He can run very fast.」めっちゃ早く走れる。足が早い！オッケー。
"He can run very fast." He can run super fast. Fast legs! Okay.
「Junior can run fast.」さすかに走るんじゃのい？ジュニアは早く走れる。
"Junior can run fast." Of course he runs! Junior can run fast.
足早が多いのじゃ。メニー、メニーファストランピポ、人間、ヒューマン。
There are a lot of fast runners. Many fast running humans.
メラーキャンランベリーファスト。メラーは、レイトかな？メラーはちょっとレイト。
Mela can run very fast. Mela is a little late, maybe?
サラマンダーよりずっと早いってちょっと切ないやつの話ってわし知っているのじゃ。
I know that sad story about running faster than a salamander.
「Yes, Anna can run very fast.」アンナはめっちゃ早く走れる。
"Yes, Anna can run very fast." Anna can run super fast.
「Yes, Ben can swim well.」ベンは泳ぐのがうまい。
"Yes, Ben can swim well." Ben is good at swimming.
What is this? なにこの会話？何この会話！泳ぎもうまいぜ、のじゃ！What is thisのじゃ？
What is this conversation?! He's good at swimming too, noja! What is this?!
「I can surf.」サーフィンできるのじゃ。サーフィンしたことないのじゃ。
"I can surf." I can surf. I've never surfed before.
「Yes, I can swim.」はい、泳げます。泳げます。
"Yes, I can swim." Yes, I can swim.
パターンだから会話ではない。あ、なるほどのじゃ！パターンなのじゃ！会話じゃないのじゃ。
It's a pattern, not a conversation. Ah, I see!
「My mom can swim.」私の母は泳げる。
"My mom can swim." My mom can swim.
マイマムキャンスイム？知らんのじゃ。メラーは、あのアイムノットグッドアットウォータースウィミング...マイヘアから火が燃えてるからファイヤー、犬かきならできるのじゃ！
My mom can swim? Wait, Mela is not good at swimming because her hair is on fire!
クロールとか普通の平泳ぎとか
...crawl, and normal swimming is fine,
そういうのはできないのじゃ。
but I can't do things like that,
うん。ドックのやつのみで切るのじゃ。
I can only do the dog paddle.
うん。のじゃ。
Noja.
お風呂入っているのじゃ。
Are you taking a bath?
お風呂入る時は火消すのじゃ。
When I take a bath, I turn off the fire.
あのワシのね髪の毛の火とね、あのどうなってるか知りたい人はね、
If you want to know what happened to Washi's hair,
昨日投稿した自己紹介動画を見るとね解明される気がしますのじゃ。
it's explained in yesterday's self-introduction video.
ぜひ見てほしいのじゃ。
Please check it out, noja!
He never drives fast.
彼は、まっネバーだから、彼はまったく決してかな、決して早く運転しない。
He never... what does "never" mean? "Mattaku"?
ネバー、ネバーって何じゃ？まったく？
Never, "never" means "mattaku"?
まったく早く運転しない、決してじゃった。
Mattaku, fast, untenshinai... Kesshiteja.
別の表現で、なんでもいいんじゃな。なんでもいいんじゃな。
Well, either is fine.
はい、yesterday is self-introduce video had more about the fire in my hair, so watch, watch that, so I said that,うん。
Yes, yesterday's self-introduction video had more about the fire in my hair, so watch that! So I said that.
どっちもオッケー。He never drives fast.
Both are okay. He never drives fast.
They can run fast!
なんか走る早さがあの、序列につながってそうな場所を早く走れたらモテる的な小学生価値観なのじゃ。
If I can run fast at places related to that ranking, I'll have that elementary school student mindset, noja.
いい調子、オッケー！
Good condition, okay!
Earlier English translation on that video,あ、not yet！
Earlier English translation on that video... Oh, not yet!
え、聞いてみよう。
Let's try listening.
いつか付けられるように、I tried to take English translation, wait for it,待ってほしいのじゃ。え、メモしとこ、忘れえないように。
So that I can add it sometime, I tried to take English translation, wait for it, wait a minute, I want you to wait, noja.
待って、付けたい、ちょっと待ってね。
Wait, I want to add it.
手元にメモがあるから書くのじゃ。
I have notes at hand, so I'll write it.
えーっと、自己紹介English translation、オッケー。
Erm, "Jikkou shoukai English translation", okay?
オッケー、I try it, noja. Wait, noja. オッケー。
Okay, I tried it, noja. Wait, noja. Okay.
He can run very fast.
Can you catch a ball?
あ、rightもあるの？なくてもいいらしい。
Oh, "right" is also there? You don't have to include it, it seems.
よね？
Yone?
あい、あい、リメンバー、覚えてるよ、覚えてるのじゃ。
I remember, I remember, noja.
あちちめらはきゅーと、right?
Achichimela is cute, right?
覚えてる、あい、あい、ノウ、あい、ノウ、知ってるのじゃ。
I remember, I know, I know, I know it, noja.
知ってるのじゃ、知ってるのじゃ、リメンバー、ライト、yes、yes、yes、yes。
I know, I know, I remember right. Yes, yes, yes, yes.
やった、やった、やった、やった、やった！のじゃ！
Yay, yay, yay, yay, yay! Noja!
わかるのじゃ。Yes.
I get it, noja. Yes.
オッケー、you guys...
Okay, you guys...
あちちめらは、so cute、right?、ライトも？
Achichimela is so cute, right? Right too?
うん、うん、うん、のじゃ。Yes.
Hmm, hmm, hmm, noja. Yes.
あちちめらはpretty cute、right?
Achichimela is pretty cute, right?
Yes、yes、yes、yes、yes、yes、yes。オッケー、あい、覚えてる。
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. Okay, I remember.
覚えてるのじゃ、リメンバー、リメンバーのじゃ。
I remember, noja.
Tom can catch a ball very well.
のじゃ！うん、yes、yes、yes。
Noja! Hmm, yes, yes, yes.
やったー！クリアなのじゃー！オッケー！
Yay! Clear, noja! Okay!
のじゃー！
Noja!
運動について話す、スポーツについて話す。
Let's talk about sports.
Kick the ball. ボールを蹴ろ。蹴れ。蹴れ？
Kick the ball. Boro-kere. Kere?
ボール蹴れ。
Boro-kere.
のじゃあ！
Noja!
Don't kick my chair!
やなやつ、椅子蹴るのだめ。
Yana yatsu, isu keru no dame.
いやなの だめ
No, that's no good.
You guys, don't kick chair.
あの シアターとかで 映画館とかでさ チェアをさ 蹴る人がいる やだ
You know, like in theaters or cinemas, there are people who kick chairs. I hate that.
やだ蹴らないで Don't kick my chair!
No, don't kick! Don't kick my chair!
やだのじゃ
No way, noja!
そう That's rude. そう Not to Not to だめ 嫌なやつ
Right? That's rude. Right? Not to... no, bad person.
だから一番後ろに座る 対策のじゃ
That's why I sit in the very back. My countermeasure, noja.
I will push your chair instead. 押さなくていいよ Don't push you. 押さなくてもいいのじゃ
"I will push your chair instead." You don't have to push. "Don't push you." You don't have to push either, noja.
Throw the ball! ボールを 投げて
Throw the ball! Throw the ball.
冒頭に動詞が来てビックリとかがつくときは命令形って習ったのじゃ 命令形
I learned that when a verb starts a sentence with an exclamation, it's the imperative form, noja!
Emma swims every day. エマは毎日泳ぎます。
Emma swims every day.
Max can't swim. マックスは泳げません。 He can't...
Max can't swim. He can't...
What? Play or plays? He can't play in the water.
なんでだろう 確かにな どういう時にすくんづんだ? なんか He plays とか
Why is that? True, though. When do you use that? Like, "He plays" or something.
なんかcan'tがなかったら can'tがなかったら I think sだと思うんじゃが
Like, if there were no "can't", if there were no "can't", I think it would be an "s".
can'tの後に after can't no s あ I know 知ってた! new I knew I knew 知ってたのじゃ知ってたのじゃ 三単現 can'tがある あ なるほど
After can't... after can't, no "s"— ah, I know! I knew it! I knew, I knew it! Third-person singular... there's a can't— ah, I see.
canのあとは原形。助動詞ってなんじゃ? What is 助動詞?
After "can", it's the base form. What is an auxiliary verb?
助動詞って何? 助動詞ってどれ? canと? can is 助動詞? 大前提が違うのじゃ!
What's an auxiliary verb? Which one is an auxiliary verb? Can? Is "can" an auxiliary verb? My premise is totally wrong, noja!
canは助動詞 あ canが助動詞 同士の原形 can とか willってのが助動詞 canとwill へー のじゃ
Can is an auxiliary verb— ah, can is an auxiliary verb, base form of verbs— can and will are auxiliary verbs, can and will. Huh, noja.
Yes, can is アウクシリアリーバーブ Auxiliary verb. 助動詞
Yes, can is an auxiliary verb. Auxiliary verb. Auxiliary verb.
えじゃあ あの無意識のうちに文法を理解していたわし なぜか選べた playがちゃんと選べたわし
So, me, who unconsciously understood grammar, for some reason managed to correctly choose "play".
麻雀知ってる口だからちょっとだけわかる ちょっと a littleわかるのじゃ
I know mahjong, so I understand a little bit. Just a little, noja.
She can throw and catch very well. めっちゃ上手うに投げたり取ったりできるのじゃ
She can throw and catch very well. She's really good at throwing and catching, noja.
She can't throw a ball. 彼女はボールを投げられないのじゃ
She can't throw a ball. She cannot throw a ball, noja.
She throws the ball far. 遠くにボールを投げます。 She can throw the ball far. 遠くにボールを投げ...ん? 違うな canじゃない
She throws the ball far. She throws the ball far. She can throw the ball far. Throw the ball... huh? Wait, no, it's not can.
She throws the ball far. 彼女は遠くにボールを投げます。 彼女は遠くにボールを投げれます。 Lisa can throw the ball far. 見て can あの助動詞のあとはsつかない
She throws the ball far. She throws the ball far. Lisa can throw the ball far. See? After can, that auxiliary verb, there's no "s".
助動詞のあとsつかない。 これはshowing you when when to use the s. 確かに
No "s" after an auxiliary verb. This is showing you when to use the "s". True.
She throws... throws the ball far. canがないね。 She can throw... sがない、no s! Lisa can throw the ball far. canだからsないのじゃ。オッケー。
She throws... throws the ball far. There's no "can". She can throw... there's no "s", no "s"! Lisa can throw the ball far. Because there's "can", there's no "s", noja. Okay.
遠い far. 遠いのじゃ。
Far. It means far, noja.
Ben, can you kick this ball? このボールを蹴れますか?
Ben, can you kick this ball? Can you kick this ball?
I can't swim. 泳げませんのじゃ。
I can't swim. I can't swim, noja.
Is Tom good at football? Yes, he makes really great cakes, not cakes...
No, he can't throw a ball very far.
フットボールって投げるの？
You throw footballs?
フットボールってさ、ハンド？
Football, is it hand... ?
あ、アメリカンフットボール！
アメリカンフットボール！オッケーオッケーオッケー。
Ah, American football! American football!
Okay, okay, okay.
アメリカンフットボールね！
オッケーオッケーオッケー。
American football, right!
Okay, okay, okay.
Your... なんちゃら？
can kick the ball very far, right? Your... neighbor かな？
Your... what's-its-name? Can kick the
ball very far, right? Your... neighbor?
ポテトじゃないし、シャンプーでもないし。
あなたの隣人は...
It's not potato, nor shampoo.
Your neighbor...
遠くにボールを蹴れます。
can kick the ball far away.
のじゃ！オッケー！
Noja! Okay!
Why are you good at soccer?
なんでサッカーそんな上手なの？
Why are you so good at soccer?
I don't have my wallet right now. What?
I can kick a ball very far.
I don't have my wallet right now.
What? I can kick a ball very far.
これ答えになってなーいのじゃ！
That doesn't make any sense, Noja!
Why are you good at soccer?
なんでそんな...あ、答えになってるか。
Why are you good at soccer? Why are
you so... Oh, that does make sense.
なんで上手なん？
Why are you so good at it?
ボール遠くに蹴れるからなのじゃ。
Because I can kick the ball far away.
まあ、まあ、まあか。まあオッケーか。
Well, I guess so. Well, okay then.
This question is too weird.
Yes, I think so too. I think so too!
This question is too weird. Yes, I
think so too. I think so too!
I can run very far.
えーと、遠くまであま...
I can't run very far.
Uh, too far... I can't run very far.
あまり遠くまで走れない。
I can't run very far.
のじゃ！
Noja!
いい調子！オッケー！
Good job! Okay!
Why are you so cute, Noja?
なんでじゃと思う？
Why do you think?
Because you guys tell me cute
many alotto...
Because you guys tell me
I'm cute a lot...
You guys tell me cute, so I am cute,
Noja! Yes! Because you said cute to me!
You guys tell me I'm cute, so I am
cute, Noja! Yes! Because you said cute!
Okay? Umm, Noja!
ええと、I can kick the ball...
Um, I can kick the ball...
とぅーふぁーって言わなくない？
Far! とぅーふぁーって聞かない。
Don't people say "too far"?
I've never heard "too far."
なんでじゃ？なんでじゃ？
とぅーふぁー聞いたことない。
Why is that? I've never heard
"too far."
のじゃ！聞いたことない！なんでじゃろ？
Very far言うけどさ。
Noja! Never heard it! Why could that
be? She says "very far," though.
なんか聞いたことあるかないかで
英語を判断している。
I judge English based on whether
I've heard it before or not.
Tooだとちょっとネガティブなニュアンス。
多すぎる、Too far is...
"Too" has a somewhat negative nuance.
Too much, too far is...
遅すぎる！
too slow!
Tooは過ぎる。Tooすぎ。
"Too" means excess. Too much.
過ぎる。じゃあ遠くじゃないのか？
Excess. So is it not far?
Too far, とうすぎる。ほおーん、
限界を超えている。
Too far, too far. Hmm,
exceeding the limit.
のじゃ！良くない！Too far is
not good. オッケーオッケーオッケー。
Noja! Not good! Too far is not
good. Okay, okay, okay.
ニュアンスが変わっちゃうのじゃ。
The nuance changes, Noja.
なるほどなのだ。ふおーん。
I see, Noja. Hmm.
コメントは...あ、でもバット、
あの問題を解く時、
The comments... But wait, when
I solve questions,
When I answer question,
when I answer question,
when I answer questions, when I
answer questions,
I don't watch comments.
So I...
I don't look at the comments. So I...
After I answer the question,
I watch comments, chat.
after I answer the questions, I look
at the comments and chat.
うん、After I answerだから、
You guysは書いていいよ。書いていいのじゃ。
Yeah, since it's "after I answer," you
guys can, um, write. You can write, Noja.
すっぽいらー？うん。
Spoilers? Yeah.
オッケーのじゃ。うん。
Okay, Noja. Yeah.
Only I answer... Umm, I don't watch
chat when I answer question. No cheating, okay?
chat when I answer. No cheating, okay?
始めるか
Shall we start?
から言うがいず、あの、
From now on, um...
can write to answer in chat. うん。
you can write the answer in chat. Yeah.
書いていいよ、because I don't watch. うん。
You can write it, because I don't look. Yeah.
のじゃ。
Noja.
OK。
Okay.
次、サッカーボールが蹴れない！ I can't kick
Next, I can't kick a soccer ball!
ボールがない。あ、ボールあった。
No ball. Ah, there's the ball.
I can't kick a soccer ball!
うん。え、
Yeah. Uh,
彼女はボールが投げられない。She can't throw a ball!
she can't throw a ball!
全問正解！グレートのじゃ！
All correct! Great, noja!
パーフェクトのじゃ！OK。
Perfect, noja! Okay.
運動について話す
Talk about exercise.
え、もあ
Uh, more.
Football? This Duolingo is so wrong!
ノートサッカー？フットボール？フットボール？
Not soccer? Football? Football?
さっきの問題がザボールだったのがもやる。
The last question was "the ball", so it's annoying.
なんて、なんて、なんて？ザボールじゃなくてアボールなのじゃ？
Why, why, why? It's "a ball" instead of "the ball"?
もしあとザの違いがあまり分かってないのじゃ。
If... I don't really understand the difference between "a" and "the".
え、Soccer? Football, yes.
Uh, Soccer? Football, yes.
これ流派すか？これ流派すか？
Is this a denomination? Is this a denomination?
OK？
Okay?
Soccer is American only? あ、OK、
Soccer is American only? Ah, OK,
なんかコメント欄でも荒れてる、チャット欄でも。
it's getting chaotic in the comment section, in chat too.
これアメリカ英語？ It's American English.
Is this American English? It's American English.
なるほどね。流派があるのね。
I see. There are denominations.
あんま触れないほうがよかった？あんま触れないほうがいいやつなのじゃ？
Should I not have touched on it? Is this better left alone, noja?
なんかあるのね。どっちかみたいなのがあって、デュオリンゴはあの、サッカーのやつ
So there's something like that. There's one or the other, and Duolingo... um, the soccer one
Japan calls it soccer too.
Yes、日本も日本でものじゃ。あ、
Yes, Japan too, in Japan too, noja. Ah,
火の用事じゃ、火の用事じゃ！
fire safety, fire safety!
のじゃのじゃのじゃ！鞭は、
Noja noja noja! Whips,
鞭は争いを生まますのじゃ！
whips breed conflict, noja!
のじゃ！なるほど、あのキノコ、タケノコ的な感じのじゃ。のじゃのじゃのじゃ。
Noja! I see, it's like mushrooms and bamboo shoots. Noja noja noja.
いやー、やはりね、あの炎上はいかにして起こるかっていう話なんじゃが、鞭なのじゃずばり。
Yeah, after all, talking about how controversies happen, it's whips, exactly.
悪いのない炎上というのは鞭によって起こりますのじゃ。
Controversies without malice happen because of whips, noja.
知らないということは罪ですのじゃ。
Not knowing is a sin, noja.
あの知らないことは実は罪ではそんなないんじゃが、表に出て配信をしたり発信活動をする人間が知らないというのはなかなかになぎりゅーてぃーですのじゃ、火の用事じゃ！
Not knowing isn't actually that much of a sin, but for someone who goes public to stream or create content to not know is quite... guilty, noja, fire safety!
オーケー、オーケーのじゃ。 Be careful for fire, OK.
Okay, okay, noja. Be careful for fire, OK.
Be careful, be careful, noja! のじゃ、fire safety first, noja!
Be careful, be careful, noja! Noja, fire safety first, noja!
よし、じゃあ重り、重り選ぶのじゃ。ネクスト！ネクストのじゃー！
Alright, then weights, choose weights, noja. Next! Next, noja!
ちなみにメェラちゃんたけのこ派ですか？燃やそうとするな！
By the way, are you Team Bamboo Shoot, Meela-chan? Don't try to burn it!
燃やそうとするな！わしの配信を、わしの配信を燃やそうとするな！のじゃ。
Don't try to burn my stream, my stream! Noja.
Wait, waitなのじゃ。
Wait, wait, noja.
あの、お答えすることは避けますのじゃ。名言は、名言することは避けさせていただきますのじゃ。
Um, I will refrain from answering. I will refrain from making a clear statement, noja.
うん、何も言わない沈黙ですのじゃ。賢い、賢いわしは沈黙を選択いたしますのじゃ。
Yeah, I won't say anything, it's silence, noja. Clever, clever me chooses silence, noja.
わしのコメント欄に放火魔がおりますのじゃ！はあ、恐ろしいのじゃ！
There is an arsonist in my comment section, noja! Hah, how terrifying, noja!
Do you also have weights at home?
重りが家にあるか？ないのじゃ。 No, noのじゃ。
Are there weights at home? There aren't, noja. No, no, noja.
答えは沈黙！ Yes, クラピカも言ってたのじゃ。沈黙が正しいのじゃ。
The answer is silence! Yes, Kurapika said so too. Silence is correct, noja.
a heavy bag - 重いカバン
a heavy bag - heavy bag
These weights are heavy!
重りヘビーじゃなかったらあんまり意味ないのじゃ。
If weights aren't heavy, there's not much point, noja.
Can he lift those weights?
リフトって何？ Can he lift those weight? 持ち上げられるとかかな？リフト
What's "lift"? Can he lift those weights? Does it mean being able to lift them or something? Lift.
持ち上げます。うーん。
Lifts... Hmm.
Can she play basketball too?
リフトが持ち上げる。リフトが持ち上げる。うーん。
Lift means to lift up. Lift means to lift up. Hmm.
リフティング？リフティングって言うよね。
Lifting? You call it lifting, right?
あの、サッカーもしくはフットボールの、あの、あのさ、
Like, for soccer or football, um, you know,
ずっとボールをかすやつ、あれリフティングっていう。あれが上げる？うーん。
the thing where you keep juggling the ball, that's called lifting. Does that mean to lift? Hmm.
もしくはって言ったらサッカーって言われてる。もしくはって言ったら、もしくはって言ったら。あ、アイセッド、もしくは？アイセッドor？アイセッドor、ゆった？アイセッドorゆったのじゃ？オッケー？うーん。
If I said "or", I said "or", right? Okay? Hmm.
うーん、ここ怖い。怖い。エンジョイ怖いのじゃ。オッケー？
Hmm, this is scary. Scary. Enjoyably scary, huh? Okay?
アイセッドor！オッケー？エス！
I said "or"! Okay? Yes!
Can Lisa surf well?
リサは上手にサーフィングできますか？
Do you lift weights at the gym?
ジムね、重りを持ち上げますか？うーん。
At the gym, do you lift weights? Hmm.
Can you do a push-up? What is push-up?
Can you do a push-up? What is a push-up?
押して上げる。
Pushing up.
なんか、ジム、ジムのやつなのかな？筋トレのやつなのかな？
Is it like, a gym thing? A workout thing?
Can you throw a ball?
メラは、メラは筋トレしない。
Mela, Mela doesn't work out.
Do you lift, bro?
アイエムノットリフト、筋トレしない。
I'm not lifting, I don't work out.
腕立て伏せ、プッシュアップはジムエクササイズ。
Push-ups are a gym exercise.
ジムの話。オッケー？
Talking about the gym. Okay?
プッシュアップ腕立て伏せ、アイ、アイ、キャントプッシュアップ、ビコーズ、イッツハード。難しいからしない。うん。
Push-ups... I can't do push-ups because it's hard. I don't do them because they're difficult. Yeah.
アイ、アクチュアリー、アイゴージム、バットアイオンリーウォーキング。ウォーキングしかしないのじゃ。うん。
Actually, I go to the gym, but I only walk. I only walk, you know. Yeah.
ウォーキング、ジャストウォーキングのじゃ。腕立て伏せ、ノーイーブンワンプッシュアップ。
Walking, just walking. Push-ups... not even one push-up.
イーブンエニワンセイミドゥ、しろって言われたらするけど、
Even if someone tells me to do it, I would,
自主的にはしないのじゃ。うん。
but voluntarily, I don't do it, you know. Yeah.
ビコーズイッツハード、ハードワーク。アイ、ドントライクハードワークのじゃ。うん。
Because it's hard work. I don't like hard work, you know. Yeah.
How many miles do you walk? ええ、マイル？マイルわかんないのじゃ。
How many miles do you walk? Eh, miles? I don't know miles, you know.
あの、キロメートルでもいい？キロメートルでもいい？あの、5キロメートルくらい歩くのじゃ。
Um, is kilometers okay? Is kilometers okay? Um, I walk about 5 kilometers, you know.
マイルがわかんない。1.6、1.6kmが1マイル。
I don't get miles. 1.6, 1.6km is 1 mile.
じゃあ、だいたい、アラウンド5マイル？うーん、3.1マイル、3.1マイルくらい歩く。
So, roughly around 5 miles? Um, walking about 3.1 miles, 3.1 miles, you know.
Wow, can she do fifty push-ups? 50回も腕立て伏せできるのじゃ？すごい！それですごいのじゃ。
Wow, can she do fifty push-ups? Can she do 50 push-ups? Amazing! That's amazing, you know.
I can't do push-ups! はい、this is me! This is me! I can't do push-ups! できない。ええと、
I can't do push-ups! Yes, this is me! This is me! I can't do push-ups! I can't. Um,
腕立て伏せができない。
I can't do push-ups.
I can't...
I can do five push-ups.
5回。まあ、5回なら、maybe I can do five, maybe.
Five times. Well, if it's 5 times, maybe I can do 5, maybe.
Can you swim? Can you swim?
Push-ups are hard! Yes, I think so too.
Push-ups are hard! Push-up, push-ups are hard. Ups なんだね。
Push-up... push-ups are hard. It's "ups", huh?
Push-up が1回だから、何回もやるとups になるんじゃ。何回もあったらs になるから、s なの？腕立て伏せはきつい。Yes, 腕立て伏せ。
Since "push-up" is once, doing it multiple times makes it "ups", right? Since there are many times, it becomes "s", so it's "s"? Push-ups are tough. Yes, push-ups.
それはきつい
That's tough.
イエス
Yes.
マルチプル
Multiple.
トム・キャン・ドゥ・トゥエンティ・プッシュアップス
Tom can do twenty push-ups.
20回、トム20回
20 times, Tom 20 times.
プッシュアップス・アー・ハード、イエス、アイ・シンク・ソートゥー
Push-ups are hard, yes, I think so too.
プッシュアップ・メーシー？
Push-up... messy?
プッシュアップ・メーシーなの？
Is push-up messy?
フッキン、ない、ノー・フッキン
Abs, none, no abs.
プッシュアップって名詞だからS、名詞だからS、名詞だからSってなんじゃ、それ知らない
Push-up is a noun, so S... wait, what? I don't know that.
ウルドセッスルができない、アイ・キャン・ドゥ・プッシュアップス
I can't do... I can do push-ups.
わあ、ワオ、ディーズ・ウェイト・アー・ヘビー
Woah, wow, these weights are heavy.
ジムへウェイトを上げてますか？・アー・ユー…違うか
Are you lifting weights at the gym? Uh, you... wait, no.
上げるが、動詞だからドゥなのか？・ドゥ・ユー・リフト・ウェイト・アット…
Lifting is a verb, so "do"? Do you lift weights at...
ドゥ・ユー・リフト・ザ・ウェイト・アット・ザ・ジム・ドゥ？
Do you lift the weights at the gym? Do?
合ってる？なんで合ってるか分かんない、ワイ！ワイ！なんで合ってるか分かんない、ワイ・エル・イズ・コレクト？
Is it right? I don't know why it's right. Why?! Why is YL correct?
分かんない、なんか適当にやったら合ってた、適当にやったら合ってたのじゃ
I don't know, I just guessed randomly and it was right.
ドゥ・ユー・リフト・ウェイト、リフトが上げる、ウェイトを上げる
Do you lift weights? "Lift" means lift, "weights" means weights.
プルール・ソー・ノウ・ジャ・ネセサリー
Plural so no "the" necessary.
ウェイト、あ、イスがあるからざがいらない
Weights, ah, because of "is", "the" isn't needed.
ユー・ドント・ニード・トゥ・スペシファイ・ザ・オブジェクト・オブ・ザ・アクション
You don't need to specify the object of the action.
プルール・ノウザ、複数形じゃない、ウェイトス
Plural no "the", not plural, weights.
特定の重みじゃない、イッツ・ノット・スペシフィック・ウェイトス、イッツ・ウェイト・イン・ジェネラル
Not specific weights, it's weights in general.
確かに、ウェイトが、ざウェイトだったら、重みが限定されてるかも
True, if it's "the weights", maybe the weight is specified.
ウェイトにこだわりがない、確かに、エニー・ウェイトだ、エニー・ウェイトだからざがいらない
No particular attachment to weights, true, it's any weights, so "the" isn't needed.
リフト・ザ・ウェイト・ザ・ウェイト、ボス、オッケー・バット・アット・ジム・イズ・ロング、アット・ザ・ジム・イズ・ライト
Lift the weights the weights, both okay, but "at gym is wrong", "at the gym is right".
なんで、あの、そ、こっちもよく分かんない、アット・ジムはダメ？ワイ？
Why, um, I don't really get this either. "At gym" is no good? Why?
なんでアット・ジャ・なのは、アット・ジムはの？ワイ、なんで、ザ・ジム・イズ・プレイス、ザ・ジム・イズ、あ、ザ・ジムでいっこなの？
Why "at the"? Why is "at gym" no good? "The gym is a place," ah, "the gym" is one set phrase?
あー、イッツ・ア・スペシフィック・ジム、確かに、ジム・ニーズ・トゥ・ビ・スペシフィック、確かに、ジムは、どのジムか分かんない、どの、確かに
Ah, it's a specific gym. True, gym needs to be specific. True, gym is... we don't know which gym.
どのジムか、分かんないとだめかも。ザ・ジム・イズ・スペシフィック・プレイス・アット・ジム・イズ・ライト、確かに
We have to know which gym, maybe. "The gym is a specific place, at the gym is right," true.
そっか、じゃあザを入れるところは、指定しなきゃいけないとこ、指定しなきゃいけないとこはザがある
I see, so where you put "the" is where you need to specify; where you need to specify, there's "the".
ちなみに、アット・ザの違いって何？ホワット・イズ・ザ・ディファレンス・オブ・ザ・とア・ザ・ジム・アンド・ア・ジムが、オーケー、オーケー、あ、分かってきた
By the way, what's the difference between "at the"? What's the difference between "the gym" and "a gym"? Ah, I'm starting to get it.
アース・ワン・アロング・メニー、ザ・イズ・スペシフィック・ワン、あー
"'A' is one among many, 'the' is the specific one, ah."
じゃあ、本当にさっき言った通りだ、なんでもいい時はア、よくわかんない時はア
So, it's just as I said earlier: when it can be anything, it's "a", when you don't really know, it's "a".
だけど
However...
なんか、きっと何のジムかわかってるんじゃの？
You probably know which gym it is, right?
何のジムかわかっていると、じゃあジム。
If you know which gym, then it's 'the' gym.
じゃあ、スペセフェッ、スペシフィック
So, speci-fec-, specific...
アー、ノー、スペシフィック。
Uh, no, specific.
どっかのジムに行く。
Go to some gym.
いろんなジムに行くなら、あ、オッケー、メニー、メニー ジム に行く
If you go to various gyms, oh okay, 'many, many gyms'...
なら、あ、じゃあ、あの、あ、何か。
Then, uh, well, um, something like...
うん、あのジム。
Yeah, 'that gym'.
じゃあ、ざ、の方が
So, 'the' is better to use
使う？
when...
そのとかがついてたら、ざ。
If words like 'that' are attached, it's 'the'.
マスタリング アーティシクル イズ スーパー インポータント フォー イングリッシュ。
Mastering articles is super important for English.
アイ シンク ソー トゥー。
I think so too.
でも、あんまりよくわからない。
Though I don't really get it well.
ランダムなチョコザップなら「a」。
A random Chocozap would be 'a'.
なるほど、ランダムなチョコザップなら「a」だけど、チョコザップまるまる点なら「the」。
I see, a random Chocozap is 'a', but a specific Chocozap is 'the'.
「the」で特定。
Specified with 'the'.
「I go to a gym on the weekend.」 you don't spe-cify which gym. 確かに。
'I go to a gym on the weekend'—you don't specify which gym. True.
じゃあ、あんまり仲良くない人には、あ、
So, for people you aren't very close with, um...
あんまり仲良くない、あの、知らない人には、あ、
For people you aren't close with, uh, people you don't know...
「Exact 3 depends on how spe-cific you are in the situation.」 確かに、確かに。
'Exact... depends on how specific you are in the situation.' True, true.
ボス、オッケー。
Both are okay.
「I go to the gym.」 The other person understands which gym you are talking about.
'I go to the gym.' The other person understands which gym you are talking about.
あ、「I go to the gym.」
Ah, 'I go to the gym.'
じゃあ、仲、いい、あ、遊びまわりたいメンバーに、「I go to the gym」っていうのは丸だけど、
So, telling close friends you want to hang out with 'I go to the gym' is fine, but...
例えば、ユーガイズ、メラグミ、ドンとノウ、ア、ウェア、ワット ジム アイ ゴー じゃん。
For example, you guys, Melagumi, don't know where—what gym I go to, right?
メラグミは、わしがどのジムに行くか知らないだろ？
Melagumi doesn't know which gym I go to, does she?
そう、メラグミは、から、あい、ウェン、アイ、トルド、メラグミ、は、
Right, so Melagumi... when I told Melagumi...
あの、アイ ゴー トゥー ア ジム？
Um, 'I go to a gym'?
そういうこと？
Is that it?
知らないよね？
You don't know, right?
知ってたら怖いだろ？知ってないだろ？知ってないだろ？ユー、ユー、マイト ビー ユー ガイズ ドンと ノー、ノウ、ワット、ウェア ジム、ワット ジム、アイ ゴー、でしょ？
It'd be scary if you knew, right? You don't know, do you? You guys might not know what—where gym, what gym I go to, right?
うん、知ってたら怖いのだろ？
Yeah, it'd be scary if you knew, right?
オッケー。
Okay.
おいおいおいおいおい。
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey.
わかってきたのだ。
I'm starting to get it.
アンダースタンド。
Understand.
ちょっとわかってきた。
I'm starting to understand a bit.
じゃあ、
So...
基本「the」のことが多いな。
Usually, it's often 'the'.
メイビー デュオリンゴ の 問題 だったらす、
Maybe if it's a Duolingo question...
「the」のことが多い？
It's often 'the'?
「A response to this question could be no I lift weights at home.」 クラリファイング ステイトメント。
'A response to this question could be no I lift weights at home.' A clarifying statement.
ふーん、なるほど、オッケーオッケーオッケー。
Hmm, I see, okay, okay, okay.
日常会話だと「the」のほうがいい。話し相手が友達そう で、確かに。
In daily conversation, 'the' is better if the person sounds like a friend. True.
基本的に友達とか近い人間いっぱい言うほらと「the」が多い。デュオリンゴメタ、確かに。
Basically, when talking to friends or close people a lot, 'the' is common. Duolingo meta, true.
メラがどのジム行ってるかかんないけど、配信でよく出るなら、いっつも話してくれてるやつネットで見る「the」つくパターンでしょ。確かに。
I don't know which gym Mela goes to, but if it comes up often on stream, it's the 'the' pattern of something always talked about. True.
確かにおわしがもしジムの話をめちゃ配信でしたら、「ああ、なんかいっつも話してるあのジムね！」ってので、その具体的にどの店舗かかんないけど、メラがいっつも話している共通認識の上の「あの」で「the」がつくのか。なるほどなのだ。
Indeed, if I talked about the gym a lot on stream, like 'Ah, that gym she always talks about!', even if you don't know the exact branch, 'the' is used because of the shared understanding of the gym Mela always talks about. I see.
「the gym」のほうが正しい。ジムは「the gym」のほうが。
'The gym' is more correct. For gyms, 'the gym' is...
分かった。分かった、分かった、分かった。オッケー。
I get it. I get it, I get it, I get it. Okay.
ノーミスでクリア、やったのだ！
Cleared with no mistakes, yay!
分かってきた。あと「the」イズ もし と 難しい イングリッシュ
I'm starting to get it. Also, 'the' is somewhat difficult English...
いっしゅ、初心者にとって
First, for beginners,
イングリッシュビギナーにとって 後がざとかは めっちゃ難しいからね
for English beginners, things like "za" later on are super difficult.
「I do karate」 カラテをします。
"I do karate." I'll select "karate".
「Do you do yoga?」 「Do you do」だって、doが2個つくよ。
"Do you do yoga?" "Do you do"—look, "do" appears twice.
do 2個つく、Do you do。
Two "do"s, "Do you do".
ダンスロボットダンスや。
It's a dancing robot dance!
Do you do yoga? あなたはヨガをしますか？ヨガを…しますか？
"Do you do yoga?" Do you do yoga? Do you... do you do yoga?
街に1つしか無いような建物ならザ。
If there's only one building in a town, it's "za".
役所的な？役所とか。
Like a government office or something.
セブンイレブンはザで、いつものセブンイレブンは…
"7-Eleven" is "za", our usual 7-Eleven is...
あ、いつものセブンイレブンがザなんじゃない？
Ah, the usual 7-Eleven is "za", right?
で、広く取るセブンイレブンがアなんじゃない？
And the 7-Eleven you take broadly is "a", right?
文脈によるなあ。
Depending on the context, you know.
文脈によらないそれも。なんかさ、例えば、コンビニの中でセブンイレブンを指定するならザだけど、
Even without context—like, if you specify 7-Eleven inside a convenience store, it's "za", but
セブンイレブンの中でもっと細かいものの話を するなら、あのときも ない？
if you're talking about something more detailed inside 7-Eleven, wouldn't it be "a" at that time too?
なんか、文脈によって変わるのじゃ。
It changes depending on the context, you see.
なんか、内容、内容によって変わらない？その、そのとき 話したい内容によって変わるのじゃ。わあ難しい！奥が深いのじゃ。
Like, depending on the content—depending on the content you want to talk about at that time, it changes. It's so deep, "za"!
いつものセブンでも聞き手が知らないなら。
What if the listener doesn't know the usual 7-Eleven?
えーー！奥が深いのじゃ！
Whoa, "za" is deep!
My karate class is at seven. マイ、カラテのクラスは、カラテ教室は7時から。 My karate class is at seven.
"My karate class is at seven." My karate class is at seven.
7時にカラテ。
Karate at seven.
ちなみに、わしもカラテ習ってたことあるのじゃ。
By the way, I used to take karate classes too.
カラテ、ある、のじゃ。
Karate... I did, you know.
My cats do yoga too! のじゃ？My cats do yoga too! キャットも？キャットも、キャットもヨガとかするのじゃ？
"My cats do yoga too!" No, wait, do cats do yoga too?
My cats do yoga too!
のじゃあ！
Noja!
うん、帯はね、全然、帯ね、白帯のまま終わったのじゃ。あのね、すぐ、すぐ終わったのじゃ。
Um, my obi—honestly, my obi stayed white the whole time and it ended just like that, you know.
あのね、なんでね、Why? I practice karateかと言うとね、あの、ストロングガールに憧れたのじゃ。
You know why? When I said, "I want to practice karate,"
Strong Girl is so cool, でしょ？
"Strong Girl is so cool, right?"
そう。Strong Salamander is so cool, でしょ？
"Strong Salamander is so cool, right?"
だから、I want to be strong、強くなりたかったんじゃが、強くなりがたかったんじゃが、から、カラテを習ったんだけど、カラテって戦うカラテと、あの形のカラテがあるのじゃ。
So, I wanted to be strong—I wanted to get stronger, so I started taking karate lessons, but you have combat karate and kata karate, you know.
なんか、だ、ダンスみたいな。なんか、ダンスみたいな覚えゲーのカラテがあって、で、わしがね習ってたのが覚えゲーのカラテなんじゃよ。
Like, dance-like... choreography karate, and what I learned was choreography karate, you know!
そう、覚えゲーのやつ。
Yeah, that choreography game stuff.
なんか、あの、戦うカラテが習いたかったのに、あの、いざ教室に入ってみたら、なんか、あの、なんだっけ？平安初段みたいな、そういうなんか覚え、覚えカラテ？覚えカラテの方に配属されて、
Like, I wanted to learn combat karate, but when I actually entered the classroom, it was like, um, Heian Shodan or something—it got assigned to choreography karate, choreography karate!
え、わしが思ってたのと違うと思って、そう、思ってたのと違って、やめたのじゃ。
And I thought it was different from what I expected, so I quit, you know.
わし本当は、わし本当は、あの、戦いたかった。I want to fight、fight, strong karateをしたかったんじゃが、うーん、なんか、あの、形、形のほうにね、配属された。
I actually really wanted to fight—I wanted to do fight, strong karate, but
うーん、それで、すごい、あの、悲しかった。そう、I'm sad、そう、で、やめた。
And I was super sad about it, so I was like, "I'm sad," and so I quit.
そう、やめたのじゃ。なんか思ってたのと違ったのじゃ。YES.
Yeah, I quit, you know. It was different from what I expected, so I quit. Yes.
これじゃな、って言えばよかった？ なんか、せっかく、え、自分がやりたいて言ってさ、習い事通わせてくれたのにさ、いや、なんかこっちじゃなくて戦うのがやりたかったのじゃって言うとちょっと、ちょっとあの、やっぱ子供ながらに、やっぱ長生きしてるからさ、
I felt like, "Is this right?" Even though I said I wanted to learn it and let me take lessons, I ended up not doing combat karate when that's what I wanted to do—
あの、わしがさ、その、人間、低学年の頃もさ、すでにさ、もう何百歳いっちゃってたからさ、変にさ、大人でさ、変に自分は大人じゃったからさ、言いづらくて。そう、せっかく、せっかく習わせてくれたのに、ちょっと言うの違うかなと思って、そう言い出せなかったのじゃ。言い出せなくてやめたのじゃ。のじゃ。
since I was already hundreds of years old even back in elementary school, acting like an adult made it hard to say. So even though they were kind enough to let me take lessons, I couldn't bring myself to say it was different from what I thought, and I couldn't speak up, so I just quit.
YES. This is my karate's... 思い出、のじゃ。YES.
Yes, this is my karate's... memories, you know. Yes.
よし。
Alright.
でも思うけど子どもは、何て使わなくていいのじゃ、本当は、本来ね。
Still, I feel kids shouldn't really use copula abbreviations... originally.
本来子どもは気を使わずにやりたいことを主張していくべきなのだじゃ。
Kids should normally assert what they want without holding back.
なぜなら幼少期にやりたいことを主張できないと大人になるともっとできなくなって、いずれそれが自分の首を絞めることになるからなのじゃ。
Because if you can't voice your desires as a child, it gets harder as an adult, eventually choking you.
分かるのじゃわし。わしは分かっておるのじゃ。
I get it. I really understand.
だからわがままになってみるのも大事なのじゃ。
So being a bit selfish is important too.
でもわがままになれる環境となれない環境ってのもあって、結構、あの、おうちによってはね、わがままに主張ができないところもあるから、それもまた難しい話しじゃなって思うのじゃ。
Though environments differ—some homes don't allow selfishness, making it a tricky topic.
環境に寄るのじゃ。いつかわがままが言える環境に主が出会えるといいなって思いますのじゃ。
It depends on the environment. I hope you all find a place where you can be selfish someday.
Where can we do yoga?
どこでヨガをやりますか？
Where do we do yoga?
文のパターンね？これは、パターンは、えっと、Whereとか疑問のWが冒頭にあって、はてながあるやつ。
Sentence pattern? This has 'Where' or a question word at the start with a question mark.
When can they join us?
Yes, you can watch.
あなたは観られます。はい。
You can watch. Yes.
見てもいいよ。
You can watch.
When can we meet?
いつわたしたち会えるのじゃ？ When can we meet? ペラぐみ。メラグミ。When can we meet? いつ会えるのじゃ？
When can we meet? When can we meet? Pera-gumi, Mela-gumi. When can we meet?
Yes, your friend can join us.
友達も一緒に参加できます。
Your friend can join us too.
We can play from five to six. 5時から6時の間に遊べます。
We can play from five to six. Between 5 and 6.
5時から6時まで一緒に遊べる。
We can play together from 5 to 6.
ちょでもジャストナウ、確かに今も合ってる。ジャストナウ、ウィア、ミーティングのじゃ。Yes、確かに、ストリーミングであってるのじゃ。Yes。
Wait, 'just now'—true, right now works too. Just now, we're meeting, noja. Yes, streaming is right. Yes.
She does karate from four to five.
1時間、4時から5時までからてをやっています。She does. Sheだからdoesなのだじゃ。
Karate from 4 to 5 for an hour. She does. It's 'does' because of 'She'.
Yes, we are meeting now. Yes, we are online, online meeting now.
Yes, we are meeting now. Yes, online meeting now.
When can we practice karate?
Where can I play tennis? どこでテニス遊べますか？
Where can I play tennis? Where can I play tennis?
karate classes、空手教室。
Karate classes, karate school.
I do yoga every day.
When can do karate? From five to seven.
いつからてやる？ 5時7時。
When do karate? 5 to 7.
一緒に空手ができる。We can do karate togetherじゃない？We can do karate together. CanのあとはDoesじゃない、Do。Do、Sつかない。
We can do karate together. Isn't it 'We can do karate together'? After 'can', it's 'do', not 'does'.
どこで空手かできますか？Where can we do karate?
Where can we do karate? Where can we do karate?
あ、人間を主語にしなきゃいけない。I have to 人間、They、何か入れなきゃいけない。Where can they do karate? 誰が空手をするか入れなきゃいけない。
Ah, we need a human subject. I have to put 'They'. 'Where can they do karate?' We need the doer.
確かに主語がない。主語がない。
True, there's no subject. No subject.
確かに…「they」なんだね。
Exactly... it's "they".
「they」なんだね。
It's "they".
We were missing a... missing a subject. Subjectを…
We were missing a... missing a subject. A subject...
Subjectが要る。
We need a subject.
いや、WeにどうSubject？オッケー。
Wait, "We" needs a subject? Okay.
で、Subjectが「they」。
So the subject is "they".
んー。「Where can they…」誰かがいる？
Hmm. "Where can they..." Who... is there?
Whoがいる。「do karate」オッケー、わかった。
"Who" is there. "do karate". Okay, I get it.
Subjectが要る。
We need a subject.
Subject「who what」、オッケー、「who what」を…
Subject "who what", okay, "who what"...
Where can do karate is for you talking about they?
んー。「for」、なるほど。
Hmm. "for", I see.
say、オッケー。
Say, okay.
私たちは9時から10時まで遊びます。
We play from 9 to 10.
あ、We。Subject！Subject！You guys are subject. We is Subject.
Ah, "We". Subject! Subject! You guys are subject. "We" is subject.
We... play...
from... We play from ten? 9 to 10?
From... We play from 10? 9 to 10?
9 to 10.
I It it needs the subject I, we, they, he, she, めら、きょうこう、すいせい。
It needs the subject: I, we, they, he, she, Mela, Kyouko, Suisei.
んー、いっぱい主語、Subjectが要る。オッケー、Subject。
Hmm, a lot of subjects. We need a subject. Okay, subject.
オッケー、どこで空手ができますか？えっと、
Okay, where can you do karate? Um...
Where can they subject?
They do karate.
Where can they do subject?
オッケー！Subjectのじゃ、「they」が入った。
Okay! The subject noja, "they" is in there.
やったのじゃー！
Yay!
えっと、オルソア、サブジェクト。
Um, also a subject.
分かった、分かってきた。
I get it, I'm starting to get it.
オッケー。
Okay.
Subject is…大切。果物、fruit。
Subject is... important. Fruit, fruit.
I eat lots of fruit. え、果物をたくさん食べます。
I eat lots of fruit. Uh, I eat lots of fruits.
あ、サラマンダーは、
Ah, salamanders...
サラマンダー don't eat fruits.
Salamanders don't eat fruits.
サラマンダーはfruits苦手。
Salamanders aren't good with fruits.
Japanese assumes you know the subject, so they don't say it.
日本語は確かに言わないかも。
Japanese definitely doesn't say it, maybe.
え、めら don't eat fruits actually. Yes.
Uh, Mela doesn't eat fruits actually. Yes.
Yes, yes、偏食。I'mね、I'm偏食なのじゃ。No fruits. 苦手。
Yes, yes, picky eater. I'm, you know, I'm a picky eater. No fruits. I hate them.
Do you like sweets?
スイーツは好き、スイーツは好き。
I like sweets, I like sweets.
スナック好き！I really like snacks, but I don't like fruits.
I love snacks! I really like snacks, but I don't like fruits.
How about vegetables? サラマンダー don't eat vegetables! Yes.
How about vegetables? Salamanders don't eat vegetables! Yes.
サラマンダー don't eat vegetables and fruits.
Salamanders don't eat vegetables and fruits.
No, no, no vegetables. No vegetables. Yes.
Too cute to be bad, too. Yes, cuteだからオッケー！
Too cute to be bad, too. Yes, because it's cute, it's okay!
Yes, I only eat meat. 肉、肉！
Yes, I only eat meat. Meat, meat!
What do you eat? Meat! 肉、焼肉！Yes. 肉。No, no サラダ。
What do you eat? Meat! Meat, yakiniku! Yes. Meat. No, no salad.
Only meat, yes, only meat. Only meat.
野菜ジュースはギリ。野菜ジュースは飲める。でも野菜ジュースが飲めるぎりぎりの野菜。
Vegetable juice is barely okay. I can drink vegetable juice. But it's the absolute limit of vegetables I can drink.
Do you cook it yourself with your fire? No, because my fire is too hot! My fire is、あの、そう… temperatureが…
Do you cook it yourself with your fire? No, because my fire is too hot! My fire is, you know, so... temperature...
めっちゃはい。
Oh, yeah.
あの、燃えてなくなっちゃう。
Um, it burns up and disappears.
あの、イブ、アイ クック ウィズ マイ ファイア？
Um, Eve, I cook with my fire?
わしの この で 料理したら、あの、なくなる。うん。
If I cook with this fire of mine, um, it disappears. Yeah.
なくなっちゃう。ベリーホット。
It disappears. Very hot.
イエス、ブルー、ブルーファイアー、イエス、ブルーフレーム、イッツ スーパーホット！
Yes, blue, blue fire, yes, blue flame, it's super hot!
イエス、スーパーホット！ワラバ ドーナツ？ライク キョーコ？
Yes, super hot! What about donuts? Like Kyoko?
イエス、アイ ラブ ドーナツ！アイ ラブ ドーナツ。うん。
Yes, I love donuts! I love donuts. Yeah.
そう、ビカム チャコール。イエス、チャコール！そう、スミになっちゃう。
So, it becomes charcoal. Yes, charcoal! So, it turns into charcoal.
トマト？ノー、トマト！
Tomato? No, tomato!
イエス、ケチャップ！アイ キャン ト イート ケチャップ、バット アイ キャン ト イート トマト。うん。
Yes, ketchup! I can't eat ketchup, but wait, I can't eat tomato. Yeah.
そう、クラブ？そう、クルーブ？エンド ミート オンリー。イエス！
So, crab? So, kelp? And meat only. Yes!
アイ、アイ ライク ライス！ライス、スキ！バット
I, I like rice! Rice, like! But
ノー、トマト、ノー、トマト、ノー、ベジタブルズ！イエス、ケチャップ！うん。うん。
No, tomato, no tomato, no vegetables! Yes, ketchup! Yeah. Yeah.
ケチャップは、オッケー。
Ketchup is okay.
あーと、メラチ、ドゥー ユー ライク フィッシュ ディッシーズ？うんっと
And, Melachi, do you like fish dishes? Um-
リトル？
A little?
アイ ライク サーモン！サーモン スキ のじゃ。
I like salmon! I like salmon.
ケチャップ オア トマト イン パスタ？
Ketchup or tomato in pasta?
ケチャップ！ケチャップ、アイ ライク ケチャップ！うん。うん。
Ketchup! Ketchup, I like ketchup! Yeah. Yeah.
サーモン コワイ けど、サーモン スキ。
Salmon is scary, but I like salmon.
江戸で何食べたか？魚！フィッシュ アンド ライス！
What did I eat in Edo? Fish! Fish and rice!
魚 食べてた のじゃ。
I used to eat fish.
ピザ？ピザ スキ？
Pizza? Do you like pizza?
メラチ ライク ピザ？イエス！アイ
Melachi like pizza? Yes! I
アイ ライク ペパロニ！ペパロニ ピザ！うん。ピザ スキ。ピザ スキ。
I like pepperoni! Pepperoni pizza! Yeah. I like pizza. I like pizza.
トースト スキ。トースト スキ。
I like toast. I like toast.
ペパロニ ピザ スキ。ビコーズ、ホワイ？オッケー、アイ、アイ トーク アバウト
I like pepperoni pizza. Because, why? Okay, I, I talk about
ホワイ アイ ライク ペパロニ ピザ、ビコーズ ペパロニ ピザ は 野菜 入ってない！
why I like pepperoni pizza, because pepperoni pizza doesn't have vegetables!
そう、ペパロニ ピザ イズ、だいたい ノー ベジタブルズ じゃない？
So, pepperoni pizza is, mostly no vegetables, right?
あの、マルゲリータ とか は 野菜 ある じゃん？トマト とか ある じゃん？
Um, Margherita and stuff have vegetables, right? Like tomato, right?
バット ペパロニ ピザ イズ、あの、ノー ベジタブルズ、ノー ベジーズ、イエス！
But pepperoni pizza is, um, no vegetables, no veggies, yes!
ソー、カラ アイ キャン イート。ノー オニオン！ノー オニオン！
So, from that I can eat. No onion! No onion!
そう、ペパロニ ピザ は ない から 食べれる。そう。イエス。イエス、イエス、イエス。
So, pepperoni pizza doesn't have it, so I can eat it. So. Yes. Yes, yes, yes.
マルゲリータ たまに トマト 入ってる のじゃ。そう。うん。
Margherita sometimes has tomato in it. So. Yeah.
タマネギ ペパロニ ピザ 入ってなくない？ペパロニ ピザ、ペパロニ ピザ の トマト は ケチャップ な のじゃ。うん。うん。
Doesn't onion pepperoni pizza have it? Pepperoni pizza, pepperoni pizza's tomato is ketchup. Yeah. Yeah.
パイナップル は、あの フルーツ だ から いけ ない。
Pineapple is, um, fruit, so I can't.
あの、ピザ に パイナップル とか そういう の じゃ なく て、そもそも アイ キャン ト イート パイナップル、ビコーズ パイナップル イズ フルーツ！
Um, not like pineapple on pizza or anything, but basically I can't eat pineapple, because pineapple is fruit!
アイ キャン ト イート フルーツ。うん。うん。
I can't eat fruit. Yeah. Yeah.
イエス、アイ キャン ト イート ベジタブル のじゃ。
Yes, I can't eat vegetables.
イエス、フルーツ の、フルーツ の じゃ。
Yes, fruit, fruit.
ノー フルーツ！ノー フルーツ！
No fruits! No fruits!
キャン、オア ドント ライク。ドント ライク。アイ ドント ライク フルーツ アンド ベジタブルズ！
Can, or don't like. Don't like. I don't like fruits and vegetables!
イチゴ も あんま 好き じゃ ない けど、ケーキ に 乗っ てる イチゴ 限り 食べ れる のじゃ。
I don't really like strawberries either, but as long as strawberries are on cake, I can eat them.
確か に フルーツ 食べ れる なら アレルギー っぽい。アレルギー は ない のじゃ。たぶん ない と 思う のじゃ。
True, if I could eat fruit it'd seem like an allergy. I don't have allergies. I probably don't think I do.
イエス、ガキ メラ！えー、バット まあ、サラマンダー は 変色 な のじゃ。
Yes, brat Mela! Eh, but well, salamander is a picky eater.
イチゴ だ と 食べ れない のじゃ。アイ キャン ト イート イチゴ。アイ ドント ライク イチゴ 大福。
I can't eat strawberries. I can't eat strawberries. I don't like strawberry daifuku.
ちょ、食べ物の話しちゃった。
Wait, I started talking about food.
たくさんの a lot of?
A lot of...
a lot of.
Can I drink this water? この水を
Can I drink this water? This water...
飲んでもいいですか。
Can I drink it?
ガキノジャ、ま、食べれないもの、好き嫌いが多すぎるから
As a brat, well, I can't eat many things because I'm too picky.
くっちゃんサラマンダー偏食、事実ですのじゃ。Yes.
Kutchan Salamander being a picky eater is a fact, yes. Yes.
オーケイ。And can I eat bread? パン食べてもいいのじゃ？ Yes.
Okay. And can I eat bread? Is it okay to eat bread? Yes.
When can you start the class? いつ授業を始められますか？
When can you start the class? When can classes begin?
太り嫌いありそう。結構食べてるけどな。
Seems like she hates getting fat. Though she eats quite a bit.
How can I feel better? どうしたら気分が良くなりますか？
How can I feel better? What can I do to feel better?
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃ？そうなの？パンケーキヘルシーじゃないって？
Noja? Is that so? Pancakes aren't healthy?
マックス、パンケーキは健康じゃない。Really? I, I taught pancakes is healthy. Why?
Max, pancakes are not healthy. Really? I thought pancakes were healthy. Why?
のじゃ！
Noja!
あ、いやが入るのか。No、No入れてないのか。Sorry、No忘れちゃった。いや。
Ah, 'no' goes in? No, I didn't put 'no'. Sorry, I forgot 'no'. Yeah.
のじゃ、I really like pancakes! I really like pancakes and I eat ate it yesterday.
Noja, I really like pancakes! I really like pancakes and I ate them yesterday.
うん、昨日食べた。そう。マイマムが作ったパンケーキ食べたのじゃ。
Yeah, I ate them yesterday. Right. I ate pancakes my mom made.
メラ、But what about tangerines? みかんは食べれる。みかん好き。
Mela, but what about tangerines? I can eat tangerines. I like tangerines.
Sugar, I like sugar! I really like sugar! Yes, Mela likes sweet stuff.
好きなのじゃ。いや、お母さんと一緒に住んでないのじゃ。マイ
I love it. No, I don't live with my mom. My...
I'm 1人暮らしだけど、マイマムが、あの、マイハウスに来て、クッキングしてくれて、作って、
I live alone, but my mom comes to my house, cooks for me, and makes...
あの、冷凍してくれる、冷凍してご飯をね、作ってね、置いてってくれるのじゃ。そう。お掃除とかもしてくれる、
...um, freezes meals for me and leaves them there. Right. She also cleans up for me,
そう。優しいのじゃ。Yes, really kind mom, dad. Yes.
yeah. She's so kind. Yes, really kind mom, dad. Yes.
クッキー作ってくれた、この前マイマムがダイヤモンドクッキー作ってくれたのじゃ。
She made me cookies. The other day, my mom made me diamond cookies.
マイマムね、ケーキとかもね作ってくれる。優しいのじゃ。Yes.
My mom also makes cakes and stuff. She's so kind. Yes.
いや、really kind. Kind momなのじゃ。うん。優しい。
Yeah, really kind. She's a kind mom. Yeah. Kind.
あ、and also my mom, my mother is doing Duolingo. My mother really like Duolingo, 毎日してる。
Ah, and also my mom, my mother is doing Duolingo. My mother really likes Duolingo, she does it every day.
そうわしのね、ま、あの、母、マイマムがね、デュオリンゴね、しててね、毎日しててね、全部クリアしちゃったらしい。
Right, my, well, um, mother, my mom, um, has been doing Duolingo every day, and apparently she cleared all of it.
マイマム、マイマムね、クリアデュオリンゴエブリ、エブリレッスン。全部のレッスンやっちゃったっぽくてね。
My mom, my mom, um, cleared Duolingo every, every lesson. It seems she did all the lessons.
メラズマザーはね、あの、全部、全クリしてね、デュオリンゴ全クリしたっぽくてね、で、今ね、あの、日本語、
Mela's mother, um, cleared everything, she seemed to have cleared all of Duolingo, and now, um, Japanese—
マイマムは今、あの、日本語を英語で学んでるのじゃ。My mother is learning Japanese with...
My mother is now, um, learning Japanese in English. My mother is learning Japanese with...
English?
そう、もう全部やっちゃったから、
Yeah, I've already finished everything,
なんか、そう、英語の
so, like, English...
英語で日本語学んでって、
learning Japanese through English,
で、なんかデュオリンゴって、なんかいろんな正解があるじゃろ？
and you know how Duolingo has various correct answers, right?
こういう言い方もできるよねみたいな正解があるっぽくて、
Like, it seems there are correct answers like "You can also say it this way."
それをなんか深刻してるらしい。デュオリンゴに。
And you apparently report those to Duolingo.
こういうのもありますみたいなの申告して、申告して、それが通ると、なんかメールで、
You report things like "We have expressions like this," and if it gets approved, you get an email saying...
あなたの申告が通りましたみたいなのが来るっぽくて、そう。
"Your report has been approved," something like that. Yeah.
そう、言語を英語に設定して日本語コースをね、学んでるっぽいのじゃ。
Yeah, it seems I'm learning the Japanese course with the language set to English.
ての、マイ、マムがやってるっての、この前教えてくれた。
My mom told me about this the other day,
ワシがデュオリンゴを始めたっつったら、やってるよつって。
when I told her I started Duolingo, she said she was doing it too.
あの、実家に帰ると、母がね、たまにね、デュオリンゴやってるのじゃ。
When I go back to my parents' house, my mom sometimes does Duolingo.
うん。マイマム、デュオリンゴやってる。
Yeah. My mum does Duolingo.
母に英語習った方がいい、確かに。
It's better to learn English from my mom, for sure.
マイマザーはね、ワシより英語できる。
My mother can speak English better than me.
うん。ワシより英語できるし、マイマムも、マイドアドも、英語ペラペラ、ペラペラペラペラ？
Yeah. She can speak English better than me, and both my mum and dad can speak English fluently—fluently?
ペラペラ、マイダドは英語喋れる、マイダドcan speak English、マイマムもmaybe can speak English。
Fluently... My dad can speak English, my dad can speak English, my mum also maybe can speak English.
アイアム、ちょっと、アイムリトル、アイムリトル、のじゃ。
I am... a little, I'm a little... you know.
ワシよりできる。父と母はわしよりできる。
She's better than me. My dad and mom are better than me.
"Eat healthy meals." 健康的な、的な、食事を、取りなさい。うん。
"Eat healthy meals." Eat a healthy... healthy meal. Yeah.
食事、ミオ。健康的な食事を食べ、ワシに言ってるの？
Meals, meal. Eat healthy meals... is it telling that to me?
アイキャント、ビコーズ、アイライク、シュガー。アイライク、スナックス。アイライク、スウィーツ、のじゃ。
"I can't, because I like sugar. I like snacks. I like sweets," you know.
"Don't eat lots of sugar." 盗聴されてる！盗聴されてる！
"Don't eat lots of sugar." I'm being wiretapped! I'm being wiretapped!
今、今ワシの、ワシの頭の中が盗聴されてるのじゃ！配信聞かれてるのじゃ！
Right now, my—my head is being wiretapped! My stream is being listened to!
"Don't eat lots of sugar"言われてる。Why? ダメ？シュガーダメ？
Being told "Don't eat lots of sugar." Why? No? Sugar no?
アイリアリーライクシュガー、ダメ？ダメなのじゃ？
I really like sugar. No? No, you know?
自分ですごい言わされてるのじゃ、のじゃあ。
I'm being made to say it myself, you know.
盗聴されてる！のじゃ！イエス！の、の、のじゃあああ！
I'm being wiretapped! You know! Yes! No, no, no, yooooou!
"Yes, vegetables are very healthy for you!"
アイノウ！知ってる！知ってるけど。
I know! I know! But I know, but...
"A big meal." 知ってるけど。
"A big meal." I know, but...
"Can you eat that big meal?" "Yes, I can."
渡る、クロス。道、ロード。橋、ブリッジ。たくさんの、lots of。招待する、invite。
Cross, cross. Road, road. Bridge, bridge. Lots of, lots of. Invite, invite.
"Lots of food." "Lots of food." たくさんの食べ物。
"Lots of food." "Lots of food." Lots of food.
"I often... cook my meals at home." 自炊もします、のじゃ。
"I often... cook my meals at home." I also cook for yourself, you know.
"No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!" のじゃあ！のじゃあ！
"No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!" You know! You know!
"Pancake is healthy!"
パンケーキは健康的小じゃ、のじゃあ。
Pancakes are healthy, you know... you know!
"Pancakes are healthy!" ヘルシーのじゃあ！
"Pancakes are healthy!" Healthy, you know!
あ、マックス。いや、マックス、パン…
Ah, Max. No, Max, pan...
パンケーキは健康的じゃない。
Pancakes are not healthy.
おわっ！
Whoa!
パンケーキ is ヘルシー。
Pancake is healthy.
のじゃあ。
Noja.
あ、レッスン6分の6だから、
Ah, it's lesson 6 out of 6,
今日はこのレッスンで終わりにしよう。
so let's finish with this lesson today.
今日はこれで終わり。
That's it for today.
これをやっておしまい、このレベルを一気に振り返ってみよう。
Let's finish this and review this level all at once.
They are yummy, but not healthy, sadly.
のじゃあ。
Noja.
ヘルシーじゃない？
Not healthy?
パンケーキ is so yummy.
Pancakes are so yummy.
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃ！また言われた。
Noja! Told again.
また、sadly、sadlyか。sadly、sadlyか。
Again, sadly, sadly? Sadly, sadly?
悲しいことに、あ、違う違う、sadly。
Sadly—oh, no, no, sadly.
ねえ、Whatってなに？ Duolingoなにのじゃ？
Hey, what is "What"? Duolingo, what is this, noja?
パンケーキ is ヘルシー。パンケーキ are not that unhealthy by themselves. It's usually the sugar syrup or jam you have on top that carry that idea. 確かに。
Pancakes are healthy. Pancakes are not that unhealthy by themselves. It's usually the sugar syrup or jam you have on top that carry that idea. True.
チョコレートシロップをね、パンケーキにね、かける。
Put chocolate syrup on pancakes.
Really yummy, のじゃ。
Really yummy, noja.
いや、マックス、パンケーキは健康的じゃない。のじゃあ！
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy. Noja!
メープルシロップ、まあ食べる、食べるが、食べるが、I like chocolateシロップの方が好き。もーあざんチョコレー…
Maple syrup—well, eat, eat, but—eat, but I like chocolate syrup better. More than chocol...
ベターざん、のじゃ？チョコレートシロップの方がもっと好き。もっと好き、のじゃ。
Better than, noja? I like chocolate syrup more. More, noja.
ホイップクリームは好き。I likeホイップクリーム。
I like whipped cream. I like whipped cream.
Do you put whipped cream on it?
えっと、When I eat pancake in my house、家で食べるときはのせない、Only chocolate syrup.
Um, "When I eat pancakes in my house," when I eat at home, I don't put any, only chocolate syrup.
ベターざん、more than is correct, but lots of people say "better than".
"Better than", "more than" is correct, but lots of people say "better than".
I like チョコレートシロップ better than メープルシロップ。Yes, you like chocolate more than maple syrup, yes. Yes, yes, yes.
I like chocolate syrup better than maple syrup. Yes, you like chocolate more than maple syrup, yes. Yes, yes, yes.
どこで karate ができますか？
Where can they do karate?
Where they can do karate? Yes?
違う、違う。Where they can do... 疑問系だから、Because it's 質問、question?
No, no. "Where they can do..." Since it's an interrogative, because it's a question, question?
Questionだから can they? ああ！
Since it's a question, can they? Ah!
疑問、確かに can が先だ。Questionだから。
A question, true, "can" comes first. Because it's a question.
さっきいけてたのに、このさっきいけてた問題がいけなくなる理由教えてあげようか？あの感でやってるから、なんというか、多分慣れでやってるから、Becauseさっきやってたのがいけなくなる。
Should I tell you why the question you were getting right earlier suddenly becomes wrong? Because you're going by intuition, doing it out of habit, so the things you were getting right earlier stop working.
わあ、あなたは読むのが速い！
Wow, you read fast!
Ben can't hike very far.
ベンはハイキングで遠くまでいけない。
Ben can't go very far hiking.
I eat lots of fruit.
たくさんの果物を食べます。
I don't eat lots of fruits.
のじゃ！
Noja!
同時にサーフィンできないのじゃ。
I can't surf at the same time, noja.
タオルだよ！タオルだよ！キャッチして！
It's a towel! It's a towel! Catch it!
Yes, your friend can join us. あんたのお友達も来ていいよ！
Yes, your friend can join us. Your friends can come too!
あのプレイヤーはいつもキャッチします。
That player always catches the ball.
いつだったら次の試合は遊べますか、のじゃ。
When can we play the next game, noja?
上手にできますか？のじゃ。
Can she surf well, noja?
それはそうなのじゃ。犬はできない、ドッグ、キャンと、サラマンダーキャン…じゃん。
That's right. Dogs can't... dog can't, salamander can...
どこで空手ができますか？
Where can they do karate?
Where、question、can、and… サブジェクト they do karate.
Where, question, can, and... subject, they do karate.
のじゃあ！
Nojaaa!
できたのじゃあ！
I did it, noja!
クリアなのじゃあ！
Stage cleared, noja!
Today's デュオリンゴ complete とのじゃあ！
Today's Duolingo is complete, noja!
お部屋に戻るのじゃあ！よいしょっ！
Back to the room, noja! Heave-ho!
のじゃEnglish コンプリートのじゃあ！Today'sのじゃEnglish…
Noja English complete, noja! Today's Noja English...
Did you have fun? Yes, really fun!
あ、except for the… あと野菜食べる、vegetables eat vegetables、eatヘルシーfoodはnot fun、でもあの…それ以外はね、うん、fun、Yes！
Ah, except for the... and eating vegetables, eat vegetables, eating healthy food is not fun, but... other than that, yeah, fun, Yes!
Great workなのじゃあ！Yes、うん、not eat veggies…
Great work, noja! Yes, um, not eat veggies...
I don't like… I don't like、I、I like pancakes. I don't like veggies、No veggies…
I don't like... I don't like, I, I like pancakes. I don't like veggies, no veggies...
No fruits no veggies、only meat、うん。
No fruits, no veggies, only meat, yup.
Give all sugary snacks to Mela. Yes, please! Please sugary fruits, please…
Give all sugary snacks to Mela. Yes, please! Please sugary fruits, please...
Veggies on pancake? No! No no no no no! Pancakeはpancake、クレープ好きなのじゃ。うん、クレープ好きなのじゃ。
Veggies on pancake? No! No no no no no! Pancakes are pancakes, I like crepes. Yup, I like crepes.
Yes, I like crepes. のじゃ。あ、ね、前回言って言って言ってなかったから言ってあげよう。
Yes, I like crepes, noja. Oh, hey, I didn't say it last time, so I'll tell you.
Where I learn long English？ どこでわし英語を学んだと思う？
Where I learn long English? Where do you think I learned English?
You guys. どこでわしは英語を学んだと思ういますか？のじゃ。
You guys. Where do you think I learned English, noja?
なんか、あの次、次教えてあげるつってたら、山！
Like, when I said I'd tell you next time, a mountain!
山、Mountain! Mountain、MommaとPapa？ Mom and Dad？
Mountain! Mountain, Momma and Papa? Mom and Dad?
留学してた？留学してない。留学？ヨーガ？今日はね、あの…映画で学んだつったよね。
Studied abroad? Didn't study abroad. Study abroad? Yoga? Today, um... I said I learned it from movies, right?
School? 掲示板？掲示板？Redditとか見てた？YouTube？
School? Message board? Message board? Did you look at Reddit or something? YouTube?
英会話教室…海外行ったことある？
English conversation class... Have you ever been abroad?
海外の山？ いや、ジャパニーズ山…ジャパニーズマウンテン？
Mountains abroad? No, Japanese mountains... Japanese mountain?
あ、yes。インターネット。サラマンダーに友達がいた？サラマンダー、1人のサラマンダー。
Ah, yes. The internet. You had a friend who's a salamander? A salamander, a single salamander.
エールの先輩？ 留学してる感じない、日本の英語教育…アニメ、ボーカロイド？
Yale's senpai? Doesn't feel like studying abroad, Japanese English education... Anime, Vocaloid?
警告市場、山、アニメ、英語教室？ じゃあ、答え…
Keiko market, mountains, anime, English school? Well then, the answer...
答えは…えーと、わしは…ちっちゃい、ちっちゃい人間…ていうか年頃の頃…えっとね…
The answer is... um, when I was... a tiny, tiny human... I mean, around that age... um...
えっとね、海外に住んでたのじゃあ。yes、そう。
Um, I lived abroad. Yes, that's right.
帰国子女イズコレクト？ うーん。
Returnee student is correct? Hmm.
人間ていうか年頃の頃わのじゃ、山から降りて、父と母に拾われて…そう、ちょっとしたときに…
When I was a human-ish age, I came down from the mountain, was picked up by my mom and dad... yeah, back then...
あの…海外に住んでた…から発音だけがいい。発音だけがいいけど…
Um... I lived abroad... so only my pronunciation is good. Only pronunciation is good, but...
あの…なんじゃ？その…文法とかはわからないのじゃ。
Um... what is it? Like... I don't know grammar and stuff.
1年しかいなかったけど。yes、only one year。そう、1年住んでて、そこで英語を覚えた。
I was only there for a year. Yes, only one year. Yeah, I lived there for a year, and learned English there.
yes、メログロアップ、オーバーシーズ？いや、ノット、グロアップだけど、あの1年いにいた。
Yes, grew up overseas? No, not grew up, but I was there for 1 year.
1年で英検2級、現地校に行ってたから、1年で発音上手くなった。
Eiken Grade 2 in 1 year, since I went to a local school, my pronunciation got good in 1 year.
yes、I lived overseas for 1 year。yes、so I remember the pronunciation, but not the grammar。
Yes, I lived overseas for 1 year. Yes, so I remember the pronunciation, but not the grammar.
yes、so…ノット・スタディ・ステイ、アーム、ファミリーで、そう、マイファミリーで、そう、いたのじゃ。
Yes, so... not study stay, um, with family, yeah, with my family, yeah, I was there.
エンド、アイ…あー、行った…ゲンチ校ってなんじゃ？ちょっと調べてよ。
And, I... um, went to... what's a local school? Let me look it up.
えっと、アイ・アクチュアリ・リブド・イン、ほにゃらら・フォー・1・イヤー、アンド・ウエント・トゥ・ア・ロカル・スクール…ローカルスクール there。
Um, I actually lived in... um... for 1 year, and went to a local school... local school there.
最初はね、日本人学校行ってたんだけど、なんかあんまり気に入らなくて…現地校に引っ越した、転校した。
At first, you know, I went to a Japanese school, but somehow I didn't like it much... so I moved to a local school, transferred schools.
Did you make friends? yes、friendsできたのじゃ。友達がね、あの日本語で手紙とか書いてくれたよ。
Did you make friends? Yes, I made friends. My friends wrote me letters in Japanese.
スペイン州ね、なんか、ローカルスクール行ってたときにね、スペイン語の授業があったのじゃ。
In Spanish state, you know, like, when I went to local school, there was a Spanish class.
カインド・フレンドいっぱいいたのじゃ。yes、オラ、can you speak spanish？あ、なんか…
There were lots of kind friends. Yes, hola, can you speak spanish? Ah, like...
yes、Hola、I know only hola。only me、わしだけ。わしだけジャパニーズ。
Yes, Hola, I know only hola. Only me, just me. Just me, Japanese.
のじゃ
Noja.
イエス
Yes.
うん
Mm.
イエス
Yes.
それほぼほにゃららに住んでたって言ってるようなもんでわ
That's basically saying you lived in... wherever,
あんま隠してないのじゃ
so I'm not really hiding it.
あんま隠してないけれど、あの名言はしていないのじゃ
I'm not really hiding it, but I haven't made any official statements either.
のじゃ
Noja.
イエス
Yes.
イエスなのじゃ
Yes, noja.
サラマンダーオアシスしかなかったのじゃ
There was only the Salamander Oasis, noja.
イエス
Yes.
うん
Mm.
のじゃ
Noja.
うん
Mm.
のじゃ
Noja.
イエスなのじゃ
Yes, noja.
そういうことだったのじゃ
So that's how it was, noja.
種明かし
Revealing the secret.
種明かしなのじゃ
Revealing the secret, noja.
イエス
Yes.
うん
Mm.
で、あの、日本に帰ったあととかも、その勉強、
And, you know, even after returning to Japan, that studying...
あの、英語の授業とかはあった、英語クラスみたいなのはあって、
um, there were English classes and stuff, like an English class,
あの、勉強はしたんじゃが、テストとかも感覚でやってしまって、
and I did study, but I ended up taking tests purely on instinct...
そう、感覚でやってしまって、気づいたら分からなくなっていたみたいな。
That's right, doing it by instinct, and before I knew it, I stopped understanding.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなっていた。
Before I knew it, it had gotten super difficult.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなって、あの、つまづいて、あの、ボロボロじゃった。
Before I knew it, it became super difficult, I stumbled, and it was a total mess.
うん、多分帰国子女あるあるだと思うんじゃが、
Mm, I think that's a classic returnee experience, but...
あの、そう、中学、高校受験まではいけたんじゃが、
um, yeah, I managed up to junior high and high school entrance exams,
高校に入って、あの文法とかもボロボロでわかんなくなっちゃって、
but once I entered high school, my grammar fell apart and I didn't understand anything,
あの、もう気づいたら、もう誰よりも英語わからないみたいになって...
and once I realized it, I was like I knew less English than anyone else...
そう、今もう、今こんな、
Yeah, and now, now like this...
から、えっと、ディオリングでね、
from there, um, on Duolingo,
ディオリングで、えっと、グラマー、グラマーを勉強する、イエス、Study grammar...
on Duolingo, um, studying grammar, grammar, yes, study grammar
英語をもっと上手にになりたい。イエス。
and I want to get better at English. Yes.
I feel like you are underate yourself. 本当？アイドセユア...
I feel like you are underrating yourself. Really? I'd say your...
English ability is better than just "I know a bit." 本当？ Really?
English ability is better than just "I know a bit." Really?
やった、Thank you, noja！
Yay, thank you, noja!
イエス、vocabulary and grammar を練習したい、と
Yes, I want to practice vocabulary and grammar,
って思って、今ーす、のじゃ。
I thought, and I'm doing it now, noja.
本当、めっちゃ上手、英語上手、めっちゃ言われる。やったのじゃ！ Thank you, noja！
Really, "You're so good at English, your English is great," people keep telling me. Yay, noja! Thank you, noja!
Yes. むにゃむにゃ...来週も、Next weekも...
Yes. Next week too...
Wednesday, Wednesday、あー...
Wednesday, Wednesday, ah...
AM7日本Standard Time...に、英語のじゃ英語をします。イエス、します。
AM 7 Japanese Standard Time... I'll do English noja English. Yes, I will.
イエス、します。See you next Wednesday, yes.
Yes, I will. See you next Wednesday, yes.
OK、See you next Wednesday, yes. Okay.
OK, See you next Wednesday, yes. Okay.
In English usually 7 AM, 7 AM. うん、スタディ自立もなのだ。コツコツ勉強して...
In English usually 7 AM, 7 AM. Yep, studying independently too. Studying steadily...
上手になって、You guys と...
and getting better, with you guys...
Only English Stream ができるようになるまで頑張りたい、のじゃ。
I want to work hard until I can do an Only English Stream, noja.
イエス、のけい。
Yes, okay.
So Tuesday evening for English speakers, yes, yes, そうなのじゃ。
So Tuesday evening for English speakers, yes, yes, that's right, noja.
がんばるのじゃ。With Kyoko sometime, yes, やりたい！
I'll do my best, noja. With Kyoko sometime, yes, I'd love to!
Kyoko と English Stream いずれやりたいのじゃ。イエス。
I want to do an English stream with Kyoko someday, noja. Yes.
野菜は、ノーベジタブル、ノーベジタブル、ノーベジタブル。ねえ！フフフ、イエス。
Vegetables? No vegetables, no vegetables, no vegetables. Haha, yes!
オーケー、じゃあ、See you next Wednesday のじゃ！
Okay then, see you next Wednesday, noja!
最後の挨拶は、「サラバジャ」が挨拶なので、サラバジャでおしまいにしますのじゃ！
My closing greeting is "Sarabadja," so let's wrap it up with "Sarabadja"!
それじゃあ、Everyone, see you next Wednesday のじゃ！サラバジャーーー！
Well then, everyone, see you next Wednesday, noja! Sarabadjaaa!
ご視聴感謝なのじゃ！
Thank you for watching!